Hi, everyone. This is
the question review
for the Pharmacology
of Dyslipidemia.
So, the first question,
we have a 60-year
-old female with a
history of osteoporosis,
and she was started on
medication for elevated LDL.
She was advised to
take this medication
several hours apart from
her daily vitamin D,
which of the following
describes the
mechanism of this
anti-hyperlipidemic.
So remember, vitamin
D is considered along
with A, E, and K to be
a fat-soluble vitamin.
So in the question,
we're asked to look at
a medication for LDL.
And we know that with
respect to LDL, we do
have bile acid resins.
The gold standard right now is
HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors.
We also have BEMPADOIC
acid, which does
not affect the muscle
and would not cause
myalgia that we
associate with statins.
And remember, with
BEMPADOIC acid,
it's going to to
inhibit acetyl-CoA.
But it's not a choice. We
do have PCSK9 inhibitors,
which can be used to
reduce LDL. They act as
monoclonal antibodies, and
they stay at the membrane
to prevent the degradation
of the receptors.
But with this medication,
we know that there is a
drug interaction with
several drugs and fat-soluble
vitamins in that this class
of medication may bind
these drugs and allow
it to be excreted
because they themselves
bind bile acids.
And when you lose bile
acids in your feces, you're
going to use up cholesterol
to replace those bile
acids. So the best answer
here is in fact going
to be the bile acid
resins. And we know that we
should space apart bile
acid resins from drugs like
thyroxine or digoxin or
or thiazide diuretics, or
fat-soluble vitamins by
about two to four hours.
Fibrates are used to reduce
triglycerides or VLDL,
and I would say probably
with fibrates, I would
expect if it was given
along with, say, a statin,
you would get more myalgia.
And the other thing
is that with fibrates,
you're going to decrease
7-alpha-hydroxylase, which
decreases bile acids.
And what will happen
because of that, you're
going to have more
cholesterol in the
bile, and that's going
to create gallstones.
So that's another adverse
effect of fibrates.
HMG-CoA reductase
inhibitors we could
expect in rare cases
liver toxicity,
especially if we are
giving those medications
with an inhibitor
of cytochrome P450.
You may also expect myalgia,
which in worst case scenario
can cause rhabdomyolysis.
The PCSK9 inhibitors
are monoclonals.
So I would probably
expect, in that case,
there may be more
infusion reactions.
And then vitamin B3 or
nicotinic acid or niacin,
probably the biggest adverse
effect will be the increase
in prostaglandins that can
cause flushing, maybe some
itchiness. So the best
answer here is going to be A,
bile acid resins. And
those drugs, if you recall,
are medications that will
not be absorbed. They
include cholesthyramine,
colestepol, and colosevolam,
where colosevolam is given
as an oral tablet. The
other two are given as a
powder that you mix in fluid.
They may increase LDL
receptor formation and
that makes it another
class of drugs that you can
give for lowering LDL,
but the effect is not
impressive as what you
would see with the statin.
And then the other thing
to know is that they're
probably considered to
be safe in, since they're
not absorbed in pregnant
patients if you need to give
them something for
hyperlipidemia and even for
pediatric patients. But as
I mentioned in the lecture,
with pediatric patients,
you can probably start
giving them a statin
around the age of 10,
especially if they have
familial hypercholesterolemia.
And again, if you're
inhibiting enterohepatic
circulation of the bile
acids, they're going to
go out in the feces,
and you're going to need
more cholesterol to
replace those bile acids.
With respect to
what's happening
with 7-alpha-hydroxylase,
Well, that's the rate
-limiting step in bile
acid synthesis. So you
would get more bile
acids made. So I could
say that with this class
of medication, as
opposed to the fibrates,
you may get some
upregulation of that enzyme.
So we have now a 60-year
-old male treated for
hyperlipidemia, and he was
brought to the emergency
department with a severe
pain in his left big toe.
And when they look at the toe,
it's inflamed,
it's warm to touch.
And when they
aspirate the joint,
there's uric acid crystals.
It was noted that
the patient had an
episode of gout
about two years ago,
which drug may have
increased this presentation.
So looking at the choices,
again, we can expect that
with phenylfibrate, again,
that is not an adverse
effect. Again, with the
fibrates, they're going to
increase gene transcription,
which happens as they
activate the PPAR receptors,
they're agonists. And as
mentioned, the biggest
adverse effect could be
myalgia if they're paired
along with statin medications
and some gallstones.
Evanacumab, okay, this
medication would be
reserved for those
patients that, again,
have the homozygous
familial hyperlipidemia.
Okay, again, it's an
infused medication that
would probably have to
be done in some type
of facility. You may
have to pre-treat,
watch if the patient has
an allergic reaction.
This medication is going to
block angiopoietin protein
3, and that's going to
increase lipoprotein lipase
and EL, which is endothelium
lipase. So these are
going to work for kind of a
little bit of both LDLs and
VLDLs, but they don't have
an effect on uric acid.
So niacin, as mentioned,
this is the one that's
going to cause the flushing,
and niacin is probably the
one that has some increase
with HDL as opposed to other
medications. but niacin and
even benpadolic acid can
increase the recovery of
uric acid from the kidney. It's
the organic acid transporter
that gets affected. So
you may have a worsening
of gout whether it be with
benpadolic acid or niacin.
Omega-3 fatty acids,
they seem to mimic
the action of
vibrates to an extent.
And they're going to
activate transcription
because they act as
activators of PPAR gamma.
And normally when we talk
about triglycerides, we
usually will start medication
when the triglycerides
are over 500 because that's
when the patient runs
the risk of getting
pancreatitis. Usually, if
it's over 150, which is the
normal limit of triglycerides,
they start to tell
the patient, make sure
you watch your diet, improve
your exercise regimen.
And then lastly, cholesterol
is a bile acid resin.
So the best answer here
is going to be niacin.
okay so niacin also i
want to say it's going to
work to stabilize free
fatty acids okay so now
we have a 54 year old
female presenting to the
clinic with new onset
tingling and redness on
her face. This began one
hour after taking a new
medication prescribed
to treat hyperlipidemia,
which of the following
would have prevented
these symptoms. So
this again looks
like perhaps we are
dealing with niacin.
And the way we
manage is as much as
we can, we want
to give this as a
a slow release formula,
whether it be the one over
the counter, which is
known as slow niacin or the
one that's prescribed, and
that is known as niospan.
So what would we give?
Well, diphenhydramine would
be more for histamine.
So if you were
maybe getting, for
example, an infusion
of maybe alirocumab,
evanocumab, you might give
diphenhydramine because
these are histamine-mediated,
okay, those reactions.
With niacin, we know it's
about prostaglandins. So,
in looking at these two
choices, I'm going to think
that B is the best one,
but let's check the others.
Intravenous fluids,
that can be for many other
types of drugs, like you
might think of maybe something
like, I don't know, you
might increase hydration if
somebody was taking, I don't
know, amphotericin, maybe
cisplatin, because we want
to, you know, flush out
the kidney of the compound.
Mesna would be used with
cyclophosphamide because
it's going to bind a
crayolin, and a crayolin
is responsible for causing
attachment in the bladder,
which can lead to something
known as hemorrhagic
cystitis. And then a
topical steroid cream
would probably not be the
right choice for this.
You might use this if
somebody has, I don't know,
some type of dermatitis
condition, but not for
niacin because we know that
the culprit of this reaction
is elevation of
prostaglandins. So something
like an NSAID would be the
best choice in this case.
So just a couple of things
now about niacin is that
it's going to stabilize free
fatty acids, and that will
decrease triglyceride
synthesis and VLDL secretion.
That will go down by about
35% to 45%. The effect
on LDL reduction is modest,
but this is the one out of
all the medications that
can actually increase HDL.
One thing that you have to
understand is that when you
combine niacin, niacin,
even with a statin, you are
opening the patient up to
myositis as well. Okay, so
this is something to
understand because I did say
that on their own, statins
are not believed to have as
much liver toxicity and
myalgia as once thought. But
when you add other medications,
Whether it be an enzyme
inhibitor like, say,
clarithromycin or this medication
or fibrates, now you do
run the risk of myalgia,
okay?
The next question I
will go over should
be, okay, yeah, so
again, I just wanted
to review the fact
that niacin flush,
Prostaglandin-mediated,
you give an NSAID or
aspirin, but again,
with aspirin, nobody
really uses aspirin
unless we're using it for
cardiovascular prophylaxis
at 81 milligrams
or you give the slow
-release formulations.
So now you have a 58
-year-old male started on
drug therapy for elevated
LDL. after not responding
to dietary modifications.
His father died
from early cardiac disease.
He presented to his
physician two months
later after starting the
drug with complaints of
leg weakness and pain.
He is concerned that
his urine resembles tea.
The drug is discontinued.
Which of the following
should the physician order?
Okay, so with this, it might
be worthy of mention if
the patient has taken
other medications. Because
I did mention that we did
have a patient that, you
know, was taking a statin and
then came to us with a
prescription for an azole.
and the azole is going to
inhibit cytochrome p450
and that can raise the
level of statins and cause
this issue so it may be
worthy of mention if they're
using other medications
from other physicians
if they're using supplements
and I explained the
whole red yeast rice thing
in the lecture as well so
the right thing is done
you're going to stop the
medication and you're
going to order other tests.
So we have cerium
creatinine BUN. Okay. If
this person really had
rhabdomyolysis, that
would be something that
could be considered.
TSH.
Okay. So probably with TSH,
I would most likely want
to order that if I was
thinking about maybe lithium,
because remember or lithium
prevents the proteolysis
of the hormone from the
colloid, and that can create
hypothyroidism. So if the
patient presented with symptoms
of, you know, bradycardia,
feeling cold, fatigue,
that might be something
you would order.
And the other one that will
come up very soon
is amiodarone.
And that's a medication that
is a class 3 antiarrhythmic.
It's going to prolong
repolarization because it
works on the potassium
channels. But this medication
is iodinated, so it can
cause hyperthyroidism.
And it also prevents the
conversion of T4 to the
active T3, and that can
lead to hypothyroidism.
CBC with differential,
this would be a concern
with, say, I don't
know, something like,
um well i can say that you
know some of the drugs that
you discussed last year
like carbamazepine okay that
can be one chloramphenicol
maybe maybe even clozapine
creatine kinase again when
we're talking about tea
colored urine and complaints
of leg weakness and pain that
should be something that
is looked at, because this
is going to be a marker for
muscle injury. So I'm going
to say that D would be the
best answer, and you would
also want to look at the
liver function, by the way,
okay?
Uric acid level,
again, that could
be what we just
discussed, something
like niacin,
or coming up when we do
drugs for TB, efembutol,
or pyrazinamide, or even
in this block, we can talk
about the thiazide diuretics
causing this effect.
So with this, I would
say D is going to be
the best answer, and
I would vote for that
as being what you
would do if the patient
comes in with this
type of presentation.
So remember, when we're
talking about rate-limiting
step in cholesterol
synthesis, this is going to
be the site of action of
statins, okay? If I was
talking about bempadolic
acid, it would be here,
acetyl-CoA, okay? And that
affects the TCA cycle, okay?
As mentioned, we have a
lot of data showing that
starting a statin will
prevent a cardiac event, okay?
I think about when patients
have stenting, usually
they'll be put on two
antiplatelet drugs, and
oftentimes they're also
given a statin, okay? Because
we know that they are
protective against
atherosclerosis, and from this
initial study, the 4S study,
they actually also saw
that patients' overall
death rate went down when
they took statins, okay?
So some of the
adverse effects to
know, again, is
hepatic toxicity.
Anybody that uses high
amounts of alcohol
or those with liver
dysfunction are going
to be very sensitive
to the hepatotoxicity.
The myopathy, along with
rhabdomyolysis, creatine
kinase would be required.
okay even with myopathy there
may be some slight increase
in fasting glucose levels
and I mentioned in the
lecture that that's very
rare it may be due to the fact
that GLUT4 is down regulated
or there may be some
increase in gluconeogenesis
and then I talked about
the drug interactions and I
talked about that you don't
use statins in pregnancy
probably the best option
would be to give in that
group a bile acid resin. If
you have a pediatric patient
that you're concerned about
because maybe they had
early cardiovascular
disease in their family, you
could probably start a statin
around 10 years of age.
The newer statins, like
atorvastatin and
maybe vasovastatin,
this can be given at any
time of day in the past like
simbastatin pravastatin we
used to tell the patients
to take it in the evening
because that is when
hmg-coa is kicking up to make
more cholesterol and then
i did mention very briefly
about the cognition
effects and statins and and
i mentioned that you know
most of the data that we
have is showing that statins
are actually protective,
especially when you're
talking about somebody with
like a vascular dementia,
where the high risk of
atherosclerosis and increase
in blood pressure puts
them at a greater risk of
vascular dementia. These
are actually protective,
okay? And it could
be the fact that, you
know, since patients
start to get, you know,
cholesterol,
elevated cholesterol,
like later in life, there
may be some like just
incidental that people, you
know, take these medications
and this is the age
where they start getting
neurocognitive effects.
I did talk about coenzyme
Q10 and the relationship
between that and ubiquinone
and it is thought that
the muscle weakness is
caused by the loss of
ubiquinone and that affects
everything going on in
the ETC, the electron
transport chain, and that might
affect the production
of ATP. But again, some
large studies took a look
at coenzyme Q10, and they
didn't find anything that
was really plausible.
Because again, you know,
what dosage will you give?
Is it going to be something
that interferes with,
say, other medications?
Or if this patient is
taking a statin, and they
also have diabetes and
hypertension? Will there
be drug interactions?
So it really, you know,
would depend on the
physician. I tend to think
that maybe it's not as good
as they say, as some of
the people say it is.
So now we have a 50-year-old
male with moderate familial
hypertriglyceridemia, and
they're treated with a
drug known to increase the
incidence of gallstones,
which is the primary
mechanism of action of this
drug. So with gallstones,
I think I refer to the fact
that you're going to have
a high level of gallstones
happening with fibrates
because Because fibrates
will actually decrease
7-alpha-hydroxylase. And
if you don't have that
enzyme, and go back to what
I said about bile acid
resins, you're not going to
make bile acids. So that
means there'll be more
cholesterol in the bile
available to create stones.
The other thing that's
important is that
we're talking about
lowering triglycerides.
So we know that this
is probably a fibrate.
So decreased receptor
recycling, that probably
to me is going to point
to maybe a drug like
alirocumab or evolocumab.
And remember, those
are the PCSK9 inhibitors.
So that's not going to
be the right answer. I
want to review because
in that group, I also
talked about a drug called
inclycerin, and
that was the one
that decreases
the messenger RNA.
And if you decrease messenger
RNA, you're not going
to make protein, and that
protein will be PCSK9, okay?
And the difference is that
that newer drug is injected
two times a year, while
the others are usually
given maybe every month or
even every two weeks, okay?
Inhibition of hepatic VLDL
secretion, that probably
is going to best match
the mechanism of niacin.
Inhibition of HMG
-CoA reductase,
those are the statins.
Inhibition of cholesterol
absorption in the small
intestines, that's going
to be azitimbi because I
mentioned that with that
medication, it's going to bind
to the Neiman-Pick
transporter. And basically what
that medication is doing
is that it's preventing
after you eat the fat that
you consume from being
absorbed into the small
intestines and making,
you know, chylomicrons
and things of that nature.
I did say that on its
own, it's not very
impressive at lowering
LDL, but when it's put
together with the statin,
you do get an impressive
reduction of LDL, okay?
And with ezitimbi,
again, if you were giving
it with the statin,
always watch, you know,
initially the liver
function test and also
for any complaints of
muscle weakness, the
myalgia. So we know that
for the fibrates, and
that's going to include
gemfibrizole or phenofibrate,
which is probably more
widely prescribed, that's
going to be the mechanism.
And then with lipoprotein
lipase, we know that
that's the one that is
going to have the overall
action. And again, this
is all due to the fact
that the fibrates act as
agonists of PPAR alpha.
Okay. So again, the
thing to remember,
and I won't be this
specific on exam,
is the the relationship between
apple protein C3 and C2.
So C2 is actually the good
one that's going to raise LPL.
Apple C3 actually lowers
LPL. So if anything, you want
to raise the LPL. Okay, so
in this case, the fact that
it's fibrate is lowering
this, that's a good thing
because that would mean that
you're raising LPL. Okay.
Again, this is as a Timbe's
mechanism of action.
Okay. So this is going to
work specifically in the gut.
And then as spoken about,
this is the PCSK9 inhibitors.
Okay. So again, these
are not first line. These
are going to be for
those patients who have a
familial hypercholesterolemia,
or they have a
clinical atherosclerosis
cardiovascular disease.
So again, thinking
about the ASCVD scores,
again, I will not ask
you about that on an
exam, because as I
mentioned, things change
rather rapidly when it
comes to guidelines.
But this would be something
that if nothing worked,
you would be given this
medication, and you would be
given an appropriate diet
and a maximally tolerated
statin, because just like
everything else, when you're
putting this with a statin
drug, you could get myalgia.
And then again, with the
neurocognitive effects that
came up, and for the most
part, what they say is that,
again, number
one, lowering your
cholesterol is actually
protective against
neurocognition, many
of the dementias.
And the other thing is
that these monoclonals have
a hard time getting
through the blood-brain
barrier. So that's another
thing that supports the fact
that this is probably
not a correct hypothesis.
So as you can see, and I
mentioned, it's not just
about you know, diet and
exercise, some patients
are prone to not having
enough LDL receptors
because without LDL
receptors, you're not going to
get LDL coming in and
getting broken down into
the cell through receptor
-mediated endocytosis,
okay? So, these drugs
keep the LDL receptor from
being broken down. And
then, as I said, with
inclarison, that's going
to have an effect at making
PCSK9. Okay, so that
goes a step further.
And again, the idea
here is it has a better
dosing. Instead
of having to take
alirocumab every two
weeks or every month,
inclaracin is the one that
you take twice a year.
Okay, everyone, thank
you for your attention.
I hope that this was helpful
actually I do think that
we reviewed some of the
main points that I will
probably test on on the exam
and maybe boards as well
so if you have anything
else please let me know and
if not have a great day
and I will see you soon bye